Guide to the Harrisville United Methodist Church, Harrisville, Butler County, Pa. Records, 1875-1979 AIS.1980.15a
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Harrisville United Methodist Church, Harrisville, Butler County, Pa. Records
1875-1979
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Harrisville United Methodist Church (Harrisville, Pa.)
AIS.1980.15a
2 microfilm_reels
The Harrisville United Methodist Church (originally named the Methodist Episcopal Church of Harrisville) was formed in 1834 by Rev. William Carl. The records span the years 1875-1979. Combined church records make up the largest series and are concentrated around the years 1903-1967.
History
The Harrisville United Methodist Church (originally named the Methodist Episcopal Church of Harrisville) was formed in 1834 by Rev. William Carl who established several religion classes in the area. Early church members included John McConnell, Josiah Hardy, Robert Walker, Robert Knowlton, Abner Gill, William H. McGill and their wives. The school house was used for religious services until a meeting house could be erected in 1842. The meeting house stood until 1896 when a new house of worship was erected.
Over the years, Harrisville pastors have frequently served the smaller congregation of the Forestville United Methodist Church (ais 80:15B). Because of this close bond between congregations, there are some overlaps in the records.
Scope and Content Notes
Records span the years 1875-1979. Combined church records make up the largest series and are concentrated around the years 1903-1967. Other records include: financial records, 1958-1973; board minutes, 1945-1975; conference reports (containing information from both the Harrisville and Forestville Churches) 1956-1970; Sunday school records, 1934-1975; records of Ladies Organizations (Ladies Aid Society, Women's Foreign Missionary Society, Women's Society of Christian Service), 1903-1966.
Records for both churches were filmed contiguously on four reels. Not all reels are full and the last of which is only one quarter full. Quality of microfilming is uneven; some segments are overexposed, others are slightly out of focus.
A very detailed preliminary inventory, prepared by Susan Himsl, can be found in the case file. It breaks down contents further than this inventory (example: baptisms; list date, name of subject, adult or infant, name of parents, date of birth, and officiating minister).
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Originally microfilmed by Slippery Rock State College Archives in June 1979. Positive copy microfilm made by the Archives of Industrial Society in 1980.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original microfilm negative retained by Slippery Rock State College Archives.
Previous Citation
Harrisville United Methodist Church, Harrisville, Butler County, Pa. Records, AIS.1980.15a, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Forestville United Methodist Church, Forestville, Butler County, Pa. Records, AIS.1980.15b, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Church records; Churches and Synagogues; Harrisville (Pa.) -- Church history; Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisville; Harrisville United Methodist Church (Harrisville, Pa.); United Methodist Church (U.S.) -- Pennsylvania -- Harrisville
- Combined Church Record, 1875-1979; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Includes: pastorial and statistical records, official church members, marriages, baptisms, and deaths.
  - v. 1, 1893-1903 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 2, 1895-1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 3, 1875-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 4, 1967-1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 5, 1903-1979 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 6, 1909-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 7, 1949-1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - v. 8, 1960-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
- Financial Records, 1958-1973; II.
  - Account books, 1958-1973 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - Minutes of the Committee of finance, 1966-1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
- Official Board Minutes, October 1945-May 1975; III.
  - Official Board Minutes, October 1945-May 1975 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
- Conference Reports, 1956-1970; IV.
  Includes information concerning the Forestville United Methodist Church (ais 80:15B Micro).
  - Conference Reports, 1956-1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 2)
- Sunday School Records, 1934-1975; V.
  - Sunday School Records, 1934-1975 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 2)
- Ladies Organizations Records, 1903-1966; VI.
  Includes: records of the Ladies Aid Society, Women's Foreign Missionary Society, and Women's Society of Christian Service.
  - Ladies Aid Society (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 2)
  - Women's Foreign Missionary Society (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 2)
  - Women's Society of Christian Service (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 2)